what you would try to do is effectively
map set of characteristics of that voice
in the model so try to predict what's
the gender of the voice what's the
potential age group of the voice what's
the emotionality of the voice and you
would hardcode all those components and
then the model will try to predict those
components and then recreate that voice
based on those
components you're listening to the AI
native Dev brought to you by Tesla
[Music]
hello everyone welcome back to the AI
native Dev I'm really excited today to
have with us mati staneski if I got that
right that's perfect that's perfect uh
who is the CEO and co-founder of 11 Labs
super excited I know mati from from the
sou the London scene for a little bit
here and really happy to have you here
thanks for taking the time guy thanks
for having me and a pleasure to be here
so if you don't know 11 Labs first I'm a
surprise second is I think uh really
established itself quickly as the leader
in AI audio right in generating uh
anywhere from just get some text audio
we'll talk about that some more to much
more elaborate and dubbing processes
just a little bit of Vital Signs uh now
have recently raised a series C a couple
hundred million bucks or 180 in the
press release and the stats are first of
all interesting in the choice of metrics
but also impressive that you've recorded
you have millions of users and they've
generated a thousand years of audio
content
a fun stat on it and clearly it's widely
adopted by well over half of the Fortune
500 companies so first of all amazing
well done thank you no it's the right
moment for these additional funds as
well I'm sure every company says that
but it feels like it's still at the very
beginning of what's possible across
audio space and the combination that we
are trying to achieve both building
research and the product work and the
application side requires a lot of those
resources to be able to do both at the
same time so building the models as high
amount of gpus infra that's actually
needed to get to get that of the ground
and we still think there's like number
of Innovations coming that we want to be
at the Forefront as we think about
multimodal models making it more
interactive more emotional and then the
application side still so many products
as we wereing about AI agent space and
bringing voice dabbing content
internationally or just producing the
content at scale yeah no amazing and
yeah there's a lot to build and I guess
on top of that the AI world moves at a
lightning pace which I guess I didn't
point out that the company is less than
three years old right that's right we
started at the beginning of 2022 so very
both my cofounder and I left our
previous companies coach used to work at
at Google before I used to work at paler
and then we swapped over at the
beginning of 2022 for the first few
months worked deeply to understand
whether the problem that we want to
solve actually exists out there and
second whether we can actually achieve
anything from the product research side
and then after a few months we we rised
our first round as we started scaling
the team and infra to bring a little bit
more of those costs outside of our own
Pockets into few others and then started
hiring so at the end of 2022 we brought
few PE first people in first three
people in so it was team of five at the
end of 2022 and then we publicly
launched at the beginning of 2023 so the
product is out there for two years the
company is out there for for three years
and the idea I know my co-founder for 15
years we've been best friends since
since high school took all the same
classes then traveled studied worked
together for the years and are still
best friends so yeah that's amazing and
that's so important being a co-founder
is it's a marriage and it's hard to find
them on the spot it happens and
sometimes successful but it's much
better when it's someone you know so
well we are so lacking that perspective
like we in high school we are the best
friends through the through the years
and through the years we always wanted
to potentially find a problem that we
are both excited about and can work on
together for after and then everything
aligned which we had a good and and
comfortable setup at the previous
companies then we had the idea that we
were excited about and we wanted to work
together so was perfect and have a a
clear things we enjoy in our work
together so it's clear split of
responsibilities and some things that we
like working together which was some of
those parts so very lucky sounds like a
very good uh beginning to it so let's
indeed maybe talk about the early days
and maybe the sort of the technical
breakthroughs right so I I know and
people like it's easy to find when you
write look for a write ups about 11 Labs
origin story how you were uh frustrated
with the dubbing uh experience you and
your co-founder uh Peter right yes of of
Polish movies of it I grew up in Israel
I'm familiar Israel fortunately has some
brace that nobody's going to bother
dubbing to uh to Hebrew not enough sort
of Hebrew speakers and therefore you see
things in in English but dubbing in in
Polish was underwhelming and you wanted
to fix that but I think that's a nice
succinct easy thing to say uh but from
there to actually technically execute
that it's not one thing and I know you
you had to break through a bunch of
walls maybe in those months that you
were exploring the ideas I guess I'm
curious what were the sort of the core
original Innovations breakthroughs or
even just problem spaces you had to to
do to deliver on this hey we want to do
AI power dubbing and you are right it's
even worse than just poor dubbing where
if you watch a foreign movie in Polish
you not only usually you would have
dabbing with low quality but you have
one voice narrating all the characters
so whether it's a male or female voice
seriously you have like one one one
person narrating everyone no emotions no
intonation they on purpose keep it even
flat so you can infer yourself the
emotions on what's Happening and the
crazy thing is of course we knew it when
when we grew up but it's still happening
for majority of content today and and
something that we know will change as
the technology evolves so maybe I a
quick background there so my my cunder
worked a lot through the years and he is
a brilliant researcher he worked doing
that at University initially spending
time on image space then working Google
on Knowledge Graph uh so closer to a
text space um and he hasn't worked on
audio but but a lot of the ideas that
that we've seen in those other sister
fields or other fields across AI we're
potentially applicable in audio and we
know that this will be something that is
possible and fixable and on the other
side from what I was seeing is that
there's no great product for the space
to really do anything with audio AI
space and then very clear problem set of
people that we were out out bounding to
of like would it actually help in your
process when we started the company what
was the sort of state-of-the-art for
audio at the time like three years ago
the what would have been like the best
product out there at the time there were
some early indications through 2022 of
some open source projects that were a
bit better but like most of the voice
quality was what we would experien with
Alexa or Siri like something that you
can immediately tell is a robot it's
robotic exactly but so we started and
when we speak about this initial problem
we started actually with building
dabbing solution so in the early 22 the
first prototype we've built was
effectively a stitch up of few of those
different steps so the first step is
understanding the speech to text part
who is saying what and what they are
saying and already in that step the
process isn't perfect because most of
the models weren't able to detect
different speakers or overlaps
accurately the speech to text was okay
for English but the element of when
things are being said was hard and the
second was hard was the time stamps of
of like exactly knowing when is that
being said so that was the first speech
to right it's more than just
transcription which maybe was a little
bit more evolved at least for English
but it's a lot more of that sort of
exactly segregation of the conversation
and the time stamps of it exactly
exactly and that's where we've seen
already the gaps that we might need to
address so spe Spees exper the first one
and maybe just to give a like wider
overview then you have the translation
part of changing from one language to
another of course in dabbing you need to
keep the length rightly the same given
you'll be dabbing in the other language
in audio unless you extend the video but
that's something that most platforms
wouldn't support so there is a
translation step and then there is the
last one which is the text to speech
step so speech to text we knew that
there are some faults there were good
open source models for the transcription
side like Nemo from Nvidia but but
really the other parts were were like
and we spend a lot of time okay can we
build that additional speaker
diarization to detect the speakers can
we build some better understanding of
time step and how we Chun that together
the translation of course something that
is a massive problem that we know we
won't be able to fix ourselves so here
we would rely on anything best that
exists at the time yeah and this is
three years ago is pre-chat GPT but it's
not pre-m gpt2 is around were you
already using those types of
Technologies exactly like through 202
2022 like you could see some of that
momentum so both gpt2 there were like
other just cable apis that we would try
and we try all of them and the truth is
like already then you had 80% of the
quality of the translation well and then
it really depended on type of content if
you had like voiceover documentary
translation was pretty good the moment
it started being like short sentences
with a lot of emotions that when it
would fall through but we would use any
external API or starting to use the
models which is also good for us because
it gave us the signal what's happening
in the field yeah and then the first
step text to speech here I think in the
very first prototypes we just used
whatever it was best there's the famous
open source project for some people in
the field called tortoise which was
incredible where you could effectively
the the first uh step change from those
Seri Alexa voices into something that
sounds human the problem with that model
was that it only performed well on the
very short segments so when you had a
longer it would Terry it wouldn't be
stable you couldn't create that voice
stability over time so we started
looking into like how we could
potentially modify it to to our own
setup uh using the the torti as a base
but that was early
2022 and you're you're my kind of lay
view a little bit think about it there's
also the notion of capturing emotion
right transcription doesn't capture
emotions doing it so you'd have to
somehow annotate that or maybe the
Polish background music Started wait not
expressing any emotions like the dubbers
there right then is that correct so like
the main thing like you want to capture
in that process of course is what is
being said how it's being said and who
says it and the how hasn't been solved
before and the way we thought about this
in those early 202 days was could we
effectively take the original voice
clone or reproduce that if we do it in a
short enough sample in that short enough
sample there will be enough of the
emotions that we can effectively take
from the original and then when we
recreate that in the other language that
short sample will carry some of that
emot tionality across but we' built this
prototype it was like this end to end
dabing with those three steps and it was
okay it was like not perfect especially
like looking now if what's possible and
we knew that all those components aren't
good enough to produce the dabbing
solution also as you think about dabbing
it's like combining those three Tech
like three different technology Stacks
which were underdeveloped at the time
and if you combine them it's in the some
of the parts wasn't greater of the parts
and at the same time we were starting to
ask a lot of the potential users
creators would you be interested in
dabbing trying to prototype based on our
work and it was very clear quickly that
the quality is slightly below where they
would actually be interested in like
pushing ahead at the time we could
deliver and then we took a step back and
that's to your second part of the
question which was to be able to solve
this problem truly instead of relying on
the technologies that exist what we
really need to build is our own models
so not rely on any of the the ones that
do exist for audio but actually go a
step step deeper and try to create our
own starting with text to speech model
and voice cloning or voice creation
model to fix that last step right which
at the same time coincided with
understanding the pain point of when we
outbound it about dubbing was like yes
dubbing is a problem out there in the
future but really if I could just do the
voiceovers more easily without my voice
if I could correct and pre-process or
postprocess and understand how the
script can sound or change the
corrections after I've done it that
would be so much more immensely helpful
so we had those the two very clear
signals of there's this big other
problem that is on the way to solve what
we set out with and then the research
isn't good enough so we actually need to
start take a step back and build our own
models and in those models did you still
break it up like when I think about
building a company in the space and do
have kind of a lot of developer audience
so if you think about how do you chunk
how do you modularize this problem did
it require thinking about dubbing as as
one thing in which you'll train some
sort of brilliant model to just take
voice in one language and and spit out
correct kind of Alternatives in another
or do did you still find kind of a need
and value in breaking it up into these
different stages that you talked about
and training a model for each of them
definitely breaking it up and training
each of them it's a it's an interesting
question because this is very true for
our work over last three years like
breaking it up and working on a separate
models but interestingly as we think
about the future we actually think it
will be more like a joint one model that
does all those actions and we can talk
about that too but but in that space it
was like let's break down the model and
let's focus on where we see the biggest
value that we can create both in terms
of the Innovation the Delta to the space
and then in terms of value to the user
so the first one was specifically text
to speech model can we create a model
that understands the text uh better than
the models that exist and based on that
understanding delivers uh a better
emotions and intonation so to make it
like more specific on an example if you
say what a wonderful day the model
should infer that okay this is likely a
positive sentence and pronounce that in
that positive way now if I said what a
wonderful day and it's let's say a
fragment of a book what a wonderful day
I said ironically the model should know
that and pronounce that very differently
and then if you have like a dialogue
sentence the model should once again
know this and be able to reflect this
dialogue between two two interactions so
we knew that the first and that was like
the first Innovation we brought into the
space was this much better context
understanding of of the text itself to
bring that now into speech so that was
in the text to speech model but it is
still not there was no product or I
don't remember a stage with 11 Labs
where you were offering a sort of V like
the transcription piece of it this is
still the text to speech piece so you're
still reliant on existing on existing
models in the first phase so that that's
yeah that's a great point so here after
we've realized how dabbing is like still
complex problem where the quality isn't
good enough but at the same time realize
in that text to speech space or
narration space there's such much bigger
opportunity let's take a step back let's
not do dabbing right initially let's
still keep it as our North Star in terms
of technical problem but initially let's
start on the thing that we know we can
solve so we took a step back put dabbing
on aide let's start with text to speech
and then we'll get to dabbing in a
company as we develop sense big Vision
small steps like you have to it's not a
very small step but you still have to
exactly aspire to that big technical
problem but there's real value in just
the text of The Voice piece exactly and
then like we knew that even if we fix
one of those components best in the
hopefully in the world then we knew that
other components are also improving
based on what we see in the field so
there is this great help of the field
just in generally doing better where at
some point translation will hopefully be
fixed to the extent we can adopt it
instead of building something ourselves
which would be such a different and hard
problem so Tex speech was first um where
we've done that Innovation and that was
like the first product around that and
the second was how you can create or
clone voices how you can create
synthetic voices or clone existing
voices and here also that was like a a
second big innovation that we brought
where traditionally when you try to
recreate a voice what you would try to
do is effectively map set of
characteristics of that voice in the
model so try to predict what's the
gender of the voice what's the potential
age group of the voice what's the
emotionality of the voice and you would
hard code all those components and then
the model would try to predict those
components and then recreate that voice
based on those components we took a
slightly different approach where
instead of us hardcoding those features
that we didn't felt represented the
voices in the right way let model decide
what those components should be so keep
it abstract to the human and model will
effectively Pi pick its own Vector
numbers for each of those
characteristics and then we found a way
where we can have a lot more of them
than usually any model would do and
reconstruct that in a better way which
is very very very aligned with in
general kind of the Transformer and LM
World type models in which instead of
trying to encode it across a thousand or
2,000 or 10,000 different properties now
you can have millions and billions in
the world over exactly how many
parameters if that's the right term to
use did you end up creating for that the
initial models were pretty small it was
like I think the first model was 100
million yeah so it's pretty small for a
model but there's no way you could have
defined 100 million different sort of
distinct attributes of a voice of the no
it was 100% it's both the Transformer
Innovation and the diffusion work was a
lot of the the ideas and the initial
bases for that that models that we've
created came from so both like great
thing which is exactly what hasn't been
happening in the audio space most of
those didn't yet bring Transformer or
diffusion models into this space and we
could leog a little bit of that space
and start T to speech inv exciting so
you had to combine um I don't know if
it's really two things but I think if I
back the journey you you started with
sort of big aspiration of dubbing you
broke it down into these different
pieces of it as you should any problem
you started with the state-of-the-art in
the moment got to a proof of concept
shall we say right or sort of some some
offering but then customer conversations
got you to appreciate that actually this
middle piece there of Tex to speech is
actually very valuable in its own right
and so you can really focus on making
that amazing and you identify the pieces
that are maybe don't have to be the
things that you excel at like
translation where you can say okay I can
rely on the ecosystem for that and then
you just said about making the text to
speech piece be incredible and ahead of
the competition and Le into that yeah
exactly and it's it's good timing that
this conversation is happening today and
like through of course through the years
we then adopted a lot of those
components from the field into the
models but the speech to text
interestingly while the transcription is
incredible with what whisper did Gemini
and few other Solutions it still is
relatively poor on those components that
were lacking like speaker diarization
time stamps time stamps are still not
there and we are as we speak today or
over the next few days we'll be
releasing our own speech detex model
which will solve all those components
that traditionally weren't good enough
so it feels like all those components
are finally three years now on are
getting into that place where
technically are solvable amazing first
of all congrats and and very excited I
get my hands on it and uh and try it out
I think we've had an exchange as I was
building an app with my son creating
sort of small YouTube shorts from some
facts and things like that as he was
playing with that at the time and we're
talking about getting the timings and
the subtitles the understandings of it
at the time so I'm very much Keen to we
ended up creating it it's like specific
very simple text that calls out facts in
YouTube shorts so yeah there's actually
like a channel for it right now and it
get some sort of some tens of thousands
of views of it and I think this is I
think you were just a few months into
the like the product was out for a few
months when I was early user so very
excited but ke to do that and also I
love the expansion element of as well
are you still a user do you know I am
still a user yeah I've used it so if you
check your inbox we've done this thing
as part of series C where we wanted to
figure out how like like we wouldn't
exist without our users and our
community which really propelled this
set of possibilities both to tell the
world what's possible but tell us what's
possible too so we did give everyone a
small all the early users I think the
first thousand users an early gift of
appreciation where they will get same
swag that we have as a team so I think
you should check your email I will check
my email I don't if I made the cut to
the first thousand maybe I don't I don't
know what the count for and they need to
be active still so it's maybe it's
should I am still a user including some
some workshops for the kids so I I love
the I just want to get a little bit into
sort of the product side so I I love the
journey and I love the both the sort of
the growth aspect of it as well focusing
on it and I think there's a lot of like
entrepreneurial learnings from it that
build out I do like I want to talk a
little bit about sort of the the the way
you package the product and the
developer experience uh but I just want
to hone in a little bit on just like
when you got started you had to innovate
and do these big things in dedon like
big research breakthroughs but now you
have a product you have millions of
users and you probably have this tension
between how much do you swing for the
fences and try to think about some brand
new thing that is amazing versus where
is it that you probably have a million
incremental things on how in Polish
these words don't get pronounced
correctly or whatever it is right making
it up how do you think about
balancing the more incremental aspects
of research versus trying to rein invent
the foundation because it is a fast
moving world you probably can't do zero
in the lad bucket yeah the I think the
EAS there's an easy answer here in the
harder truth around it but easy answer
we still think you you just not do
Innovation or new models or to make it
more concrete we actually think that
there will be one or two new model
breakthroughs that are required in the
audio space to really get it to the
another level if you were to rely on
current infrastructure and just improve
some of the pieces it's it's not going
to solve the problems you to solve
especially as we think about agentic
workflows where you need to add voice in
like interactions and customer support
call centers or education where you like
learn uh something that's going to
require very different type of
experience so the thing will happen over
this year and hopefully will be one of
the first to do it well is going to be
multimodel approach which effectively
combines the llms the reasoning side and
and the audio state-of-the-art here what
we would do is effectively use our
state-of-the-art models use the open
source llms fuse them together fusing
isn't an easy task and then create a
multimodal experience that is
effectively what people will refer to as
voice too you don't go through those
steps in the in the middle which should
help for everything from understanding
the emotion better to doing dabbing
better to doing that interactive
experiences better and this is so
important that if we didn't do it what
we think would happen is that we would
create an okay company that will be
there for the next five years do set of
use cases but not company that we would
love to create which is like still
leading on the research side hopefully
is here for a few more decades and is
leading from that research perspective
in terms of what's possible now the so
that's the easy answer that like you
need to and that's where we actually
took an active choice to like overweight
towards doing the innovation in the
models and potentially sacrifice some of
our lead with the current generation of
models because of how much we believe
that the new generation will be
important would be important although
that is very Ed Case specific voice to
voice I I can I know intuitively see how
that would be beneficial it feels like
any intermediary representation like
getting it down to text probably loses
so much information uh you have to be
able to get at end end but also we just
spoke about how text to speech is also
on its own very valuable so I guess just
ask as the the software kind of geek in
me might say is there a format in which
you can represent something as an
intermediate so that we can people can
create text like that does it have to be
the sort of the uh blackbox brain that
just gets trained and sort of all
knowing I am I'm being a little bit fous
here does it or can you represent
something in the middle it's a tricky
question but it's like still even with
that fused approach you will definitely
have the same component so even if the
the backbone is a model that has
combination of audio and LMS you can
still effectively create like a fine
tune version which is text to speech
model and it's better than the existing
ones and maybe to make it like an a
specific example let's take a a
narration of of a book today you give a
text it understands somewhat the context
and can deliver the audio pretty good to
the human level quality in some cases of
narration but what it couldn't do is for
example detect the different speakers in
that book and assign different voices or
create sounds and that's what we think
the multimodal approach will bring where
if you listen to the book it will be
like more like a a movie or immersive
experience where all the voices are
created and assigned that you can have
that that different set of narration or
narrators when you hear a scene about
say thunderstorm you hear raindrops in
the background so there's a much bigger
brain behind that model so yes you'll
definitely have those separate models
with higher brain power than what was
possible before but your point earlier
on is is spot on which is it will take a
while before those models are stable
they are as good off the quality in
audio and as you think about a lot of
our big set of clients on the Enterprise
side we work with over 500 different
companies of of of bigger size it will
likely not be at the level of quality
they require for the next year maybe
next two years and that's to your second
and the harder part of this question is
initially we overweighted took almost no
we need to do all on the research and
innovate on the next model right let's
not do anything on the current and then
we realized after pretty quickly but
after a few months maybe a bit slowly
once a good customers yeah you cannot
just abandon a lot of the the work
that's required to make that one or two%
differences to get it a little bit
better so now we use we have our
research core research team builds the
new models and then we have research
engineering team that tries to improve
the current generation of models like
how we can really cut it to close that
Gap and make sure that the it's whether
it's 95% today and we can get it to 96
or recently one of the things we've done
was we we had a model which was text to
speech model which was great for
interactive use cases had like roughly
200 milliseconds of the time to first
bite and then another model got created
that from a competitor that was roughly
100 milliseconds and it felt okay what
how much time do we invest and and still
wanted to show to our customers that yes
we are the leading Labs so our research
engineering team brought it back to 75
milliseconds we have a great researchers
Max and Tony that pushed it across and
now we have the fastest model and that's
interesting I'm I'm going to go back a
little bit to organization later but but
you described these not just as a
percentage investment but actually
literally different teams so you have
one team there might be multiple under
them but one part of the orc focusing on
the more sort of big swings try to
reinvent what is the status quo and then
another that is more on optimization and
is it a different what would be the
difference between the profiles of the
individuals you'd have in one team
versus the other is it just allocation
or is it actual different skills there's
some definitely there's some overlap
where you could imagine one person being
closer to the other but roughly research
our research team is extremely small and
here these are mostly the people that we
believe can create net new ideas net new
work new breakthroughs for the world so
they could create a paper that we
believe could be one of the top papers
on Europe orml or any of the other
conferences so they need to be really
well vered in this space and I think
we've been able to accomplish when with
my co-founder who I think is a genius
level and and pushing all of the
research and one of the best researchers
that we have was able to bring a lot of
the other researchers that love working
in that space and are at that level so
few world-class researchers that are the
best in the world and then research
Engineers are usually more uh people
that we think you could give them any
paper and they could Implement that
paper it would be a bit harder for them
to create those new net new ideas or
create the papers themselves but if you
give them any piece of work they could
likely replicate it and make it slightly
better or tweak it and for research
Engineers to also make it a little bit
more concretely on how we frequently
stuff those people researchers we just
get from wherever we see the piece of
achievement on open source or paper or
through recommendation these are like
the top people we think there's maybe
hundred in the world that the pool of c
does what we know research Engineers we
usually start with people that join as
software Engineers maybe with some ml
experience and then if they are proving
themselves in a core product we can
bring them into research engineering
space got it yeah very interesting on it
and numbers wise probably that first
team the research team extremely
selective in so of the skills that you
bring into that but probably
numbers-wise a lot smaller than the
research engineering uh both still
pretty small I'm impressive what they
can do but it's it's a part of the
funding part of getting the funding we
have five researchers and and five to 10
research Engineers oh yeah very tiny
yeah yeah amazing how much how much
output they they 100% 100% so let's talk
a little bit about you've been on IBM
right I sadly I don't have sadly I
really actually when I was at IBM which
I got acquired into with my company the
IBM research was actually quite
interesting to me but I do not have a
degree and so the one primary thing that
was well out of my reach was I research
got it got it I've recently read about
this concept that they didn't know of
course this applies across the
organization and some of the ideas we
try to steal but I think they had was
one which when IBM became this Big Bam
of like how do you keep that Innovation
going and they created this concept of
wild duck so you had uh wild ducks were
eight people selected and Reporting
directly to the the the the founders
which just had a free mandate on just
going after any idea that they thought
will push the business forward and
sometimes I feel about our research is
it's kept a little separate so they can
really innovate something they can do
something well yeah yeah that's
interesting I've not heard of it when I
was at IBM and who knows maybe I would
have stayed at IBM a little bit longer
if I get to be part of those uh maybe
switching a little bit back more to
interacting with your platform and I
want to talk about developer experience
in apis I just mentioned how I have used
your apis on it it's a good pleasant
experience using those and I was very
much using the modular pieces like
literally here's a piece of text get me
give me back some audio here's more
parameters more sort of tweaks not AI
parameters and and I I think for a while
that was your only API type building
blocks a platform a model and I think
we'll talk in general about the
evolution towards app but I think on the
API front you now if you open up the 11
Labs API page you'll see
conversationally AI you'd see pieces
that are more end to end of sorts like
they provide a more complete
functionality so I guess my question is
one is just I'm interested a little bit
on the journey from one to the other
what made you do it and and maybe even
when you think about someone building on
top of the platform what are you seeking
or optimizing for is it more about the
full unit is it more about the pieces
how do you think about it that's a big
question and definitely our approach
evolved over over time or expanded over
time but let start with the story just
like how did this conversational AI kind
of a piece came to be and how do you
think about it so starting from there
it's as you've said initially we had
text to speech voices and we didn't have
much more of the other components in the
conversational stack but what we've seen
happen is both developers and and our
Enterprise clients effectively what they
were doing is using that component and
building a conversational experience and
now it's not a simple thing to do it
takes usually months of implementation
time to do it well if you like we are
speaking now you will adjust your
emotions you want to make it relatively
smooth and quick when you respond to
each other maybe you want to interrupt
each other and then get responses
responses back I wouldn't interrupt you
in a minut sorry
come but this is exactly what we've seen
being tried to solve across across so
many of of the clients and it wasn't
easy everybody had a slightly different
approach it was not always great
experience for the end user and and it
was a complex problem which was like
great one thing we know we should and
want to provide is help provide that end
to end solution so people don't have to
build from scratch but something that we
can bring to the table and then two as
we buildt so closely to the research
pieces we can actually optimize it even
better for how to optimize for
turn-taking or or interruptions to to
make it smoother because we can embeds a
few uh predictors on both sides of like
when will the speech when I will stop
speaking or will the content will go to
the pause and and that's how kind of the
element came to be where we decided
let's meet our customers where they are
let's try to build solutions that are
actually solving their entire problem
versus part of their problem right and
and the conversational AI was one of the
big steps in doing that yeah but but
conversational search interrupt I'm
going to be self-conscious every time I
interruped talk about interruptions as
you as you do the work to allow your
customers to handle interruptions more
often like why pick that right you
probably have you have these millions of
users you have conversational AI as one
common use case but there are probably
many others and I don't know exact
prevalence but I don't even know if
conversational AI is any sort of like
majority of the use cases it's probably
some single digit maybe sub 20% usage no
the so it's low double digits no maybe
not low uh medium double digit percent
but the interesting thing is that like
in general we think voice will be the
future of interactions the digital
interactions of how you interact with
interfaces of of the digital world and
it can carry so much more emotion so
much understanding than text and the
pleora of use cases is wide and happy to
speak about some of those too but maybe
to give two quick examples like from
Healthcare space where you can work with
nurses we work with company like
Hippocratic which will try to automate
the process where nurses call patients
to remind them about taking medicine or
asking about how they are feeling people
that frequently cannot use computer at
the same level of proficiency such a
great use case so much of potential of
reaching the people and then completely
different side company like dis gen
which helps train 911 responders so they
can speak with the potential person
understand how to respond in that
emotional situation um and similarly
massive scale then customer support call
centers new ways of digital media so we
see it even if today it's a little bit
smaller although it's starting to get
some momentum in the next five years it
will be one of the key models and then
the second it was definitely one of the
places where we knew we can provide that
that solution so conversational AI is
like probably one of the categories
which we believe will be one of the the
biggest the flip side of that question
is going to be more interesting of we
youve probably seen so many different
companies trying to build a gentic
workflows it's clearly becoming a buz
wart so there will be an interesting
competition of competing for talent
competing for attention right that that
will be harder but going back to your to
your other part of the question as we
think about our work we have have on one
side creators that use the platform and
the entirety of our audio tools across
effectively the interface right then we
have a big group of developers that will
use and deploy the API or try new use
cases and from the start one thing we
are trying to do was bring the interface
and the API roughly at the same time so
people can easily built with it can show
that what's possible to the world and
then of course third group the big one
is Enterprises where you do need end to
solution and that's where like our focus
is is being built so at the core we are
providing horizontal layer for
everything AIO AI whether it's text to
speech voices text to sound effects in
the future speech to text and then for
our business parts we are hoping and and
are building endtoend solutions for
specific things that we believe are
important conversational one for
specific sectors and the second one is
is Media entertainment where we provide
a dubbing solution for end to end work
yeah interesting as a complete path and
I guess can you share today indeed you
can use 11 Labs through the through the
UI and create a bunch of of audio pieces
and I've done the the amateur version of
it but I'm sure there's full-on business
use cases for it and you can do the
developers what would you say is the
rough split today in terms of platform
usage is it is it mostly are you mostly
a platform or mostly an offering today
like mostly a a product yeah the
probably the most frustrating answer
which is it depends on the user group
given we have so many but starting with
like high level numbers it's mostly
platform for selfer subscription users
so like the creators of the space where
we have millions of people coming for
our platform are going to be using the
platform as the interface of combining
those components and then as you shift
further up to to either small medium
businesses or Enterprises it will be
majority of of API users now within
those groups there are like very clear
distinctions that we will see so for
example gaming companies that we work
with Will mostly use the API now any
media Entertainment Company that's
creating ads voice overs dabs them will
use the UI conversational AI this is an
interesting one because conversational
AI is at the end of the day you
configure things in the interface but
you are an API user like you need to
configure that in your application
connect it to your knowas it is a
solution though it is not it's not a
building block it is you might need to
build on top of it but it's done the the
The Lion Share of your conversational AI
functionality 100% 100% but then you do
need that link at the end of connecting
to your CRM or knowledge bases to to go
through through the API pieces but with
this like end to end solution where you
can configure all those components
through the platform and what are the
set of constraints that you need to
build in place how do you do the end
tooling what are some of the security
parameters you want to set voices
latency configuration so there's a
pretty wide set that that we provide
which is like common across across the
problem set that that we see and of
course op so much on Incredible use
cases too yeah and and I guess maybe
this's a slightly tricky question but
there are a lot of AI applications today
that are being built all sorts of
startups Innovative teams and if they
need an audio component of it they might
go to 11 Labs as as their solution for
it uh and oftentimes for companies
building like that it's there's a bit of
a a scary relationship with the
foundation models including maybe a
little bit less scary in audio I don't
know maybe just less discussed but
there's a bit of a concern okay if I'm
building something that is audio related
will 11 Labs or I'm just rusing us
example of any of the foundation models
expand to cover this space and how do I
how do I kind of balance or manage that
risk do you have any guidance people
must ask you that question of hey I'm
building this on top of your platform
are you gonna expand into my space how
what type of answer do you give them the
so it's interesting because we also have
seen the opposite of that problem and I
will answer your question too but we've
seen exactly the opposite in the
approach we've taken which probably some
of the hardest moments in the in 2023 at
the end of 2023 were due to that where
we kept our a is extremely open and we
wanted to solve set of use cases and
we've seen people solve the use cases
that we wanted to solve before us and
take all the take all the users Market
opportunity exactly the closest one and
probably like one of the mo moments
which was emotionally frustrating was
with dabbing where we started with
dabbing we created Tex to speed we
created all those components and then in
2023 we we were offering all the apis
openly and we were planning to launch
our own new dabbing solution or the
first like true dabbing package solution
with our apis in the product in like
roughly Q3 of 2023 we told it to one of
our clients maybe it was unrelated and
this client released their own dabbing
two weeks before us and took all the
users that we wanted took our vision
away from us which was like okay not
happy especially how close this was in
our origin of course we double down and
are continuing to work on that but the
guidance in general for us is like we
will keep the horizontal um solution up
there we are really focusing on on very
small subset of the work um the one is
within conversational AI space how we
can create more immersive media
experiences more interactive media
experiences how we can work in call
centers and build that that audio
element there and potentially uh uh
potentially some of the close to call
center elements but not entirely a
customer support um then the rest we are
a partner we want to effectively
wherever the research allows us to
provide you an advantage from the
product perspective that's where we'll
go the rest we will keep it open and on
the media entertainment side the the the
thing that we started with building like
an entire process for creating dabbing
is going to be important and maybe to
take a another element what we want do
is focus on on video we focus on text
manipulation to a large extent so any of
the use cases building with that have
the natural advantage and similarly what
we've seen is that if you work with both
with the companies or users know this
better than than I do it's like there's
so much n integration that will need to
happen for most most of these cases
apart from the on mentioned we are not
planning to cover and that's where a lot
of startups or companies building on top
of 11 UPS go yeah that's good I I love
the clarity I think probably when you're
building on top of a platform there's no
guarantees in life and Company
strategies change and opportunities
arise but fundamentally you want to the
challenge I think that happens in the
foundation world is more when there just
there isn't declarative statement of
these are the domains if you're going to
be in these and you're building on 11
Labs you might get yourself in trouble
and so you can do that you might be
competing on the platform with the
platform that you are building on top of
100% although we saw interesting sorry
now I interrupted you but we saw the
same we we you know it's it's something
that we think about too it's like we
want to allow so many companies and
individuals to build how do we make sure
that they are they feel that
transparency too and when we were
entering conversational space for some
of the companies that were closer to
that we let them know before that this
is something that we happening we had a
ation and an interesting thing happened
where then for most of them they
effectively saw this as a potential
Advantage where they can now provide
that conversational components inside
their platform and focus on the
additional parts to bring the End
customer with the specific integration
for healthcare and how do you connect to
the systems on the hospital so that was
like an interesting when the ocean Rises
all the BS yeah you want to know which
parts I guess one aspect of it is where
is it that you might compete with me and
the other other aspect is how do I know
that you will continue investing in this
space and so the Declaration helps on
both fronts so I think maybe just
continuing a little bit on the sort of
app and product uh path and and we'll
talk a little bit about org I guess if
you cast your eyes five years out and
you think about where is the the value
that you are providing how does sort of
the company look I think today I would
characterize you as it's still like
predominantly a a a core model you are
able to do this text of speech now spe
to text better than than anyone and
you're you're building that out and
people build on top of you and you have
those Solutions do you first of all do
you agree with that characterization
today and when you cast your eyes three
five years out which is you know more
than double the company's lifespan right
right do you do you think that shifts do
you think the foundation model give you
like a right to play and and becomes a
critical feature but no longer a
defining feature yeah there world will
be interesting in the next two years so
on the characterization I like what we
started the company with and still so
much believe this is that you need both
you need to innovate if you are to
create like a company of the scale we
want you need to do research side then
you need to do the product side and I
think we've been able to build some of
the major Innovations on the research
side we haven't yet built some of the
major Innovations on the product side
although I think the conversational AI
solution is the first one that brings
some of that to reality where you can
really have the full package workflow
and the dabbing is similarly that
product aspect but I think it's still
still early in terms of the adoption of
that product as we think about the world
so maybe a spin on that first
characterization pieces I think from
company perspective we've built
incredible research we've built great
set of products in terms of the adoption
the research is already heavily adopted
as we think about our work the product
is just getting started of where we will
will go now to the second question as we
think about the five years from now I
think the things we would love to to
continue being characterized at is that
we were able to push that envelope of
the for research forward the multimodel
AI audio experiences and really being
the ones that fixed speech as a category
audio intelligence as a category where
you can understand who is saying what
you can recreate that to the human or
better performance and whether that's
that interactive experience or a
multilingual experience we can do that
across all languages so we want to be
like known as one of the research apps
if you want to join this is the place to
go but the second one is have the
full-fledged audio platform form where
regardless of the workflow or use case
you want to build on top you have the
components and the solutions ready for
that and I I hope it's going to be much
quicker than next five years we think
it's going to be that next year or two
is exactly like we spoke a bit earlier
have those few cases where we go super
deep let's take dabbing as an example we
want to be able for you to create a dab
on our platform we want to connect it to
the live streaming event so you could
dab it on live with the work so like
next time so we worked with Lex Freedman
for example who dabed his conversation
when he was with president vadir zinsky
of course we dab that in the process
afterwards but what if in the future you
could have that conversation between
them where they speak original languages
yeah and that is generally like a holy
grail of be able to communicate cross
languages live in real time 100% like
the cultural educational barus is is
incredible and then the like how can we
help in the conversational space go the
Deep solution for call centers where if
you are building that that application
like recently as part of CC we brought
in do Telecom on one of the backers how
would that look in the future where
you're are taking those calls at scale
where it's not like it is today where
you're trying call calls any customer
support usually you're waiting for a
long time you're frustrated that they
don't understand you they don't have the
right details and and swapping that that
like immediate great experience right on
the flight that you and that's a good
example where You' need to think do you
go all the way to also knowing what it
is that you're supposed to say so
understanding the support cases and the
needs or are you the enabler the
conversation aspect of it but someone
else comes along you're plug in with
whatever solution of choice uh it is
that sort of provides the the actual
knowledge base interesting and and I so
I I take from that you say okay we still
think that the fundamentally it would be
a defining feature that we're The
Cutting Edge but we will also continue
to invest in making it more accessible
and aligned for the specific use cases
that we focus on 100% And you think like
when you envision the sort of this world
of foundation models and everybody's
throwing multiple billion and many kind
of resources at it of all types do you
still Envision the audio focus even with
the multimodel as in audio to audio the
different definitions maybe than than
maybe some others would have come to
mind when they say multimodal you're how
do you think about that as a discrete
slice of the foundational model World
versus the all knowing brain maybe that
some sort of AGI ASI type path that
we're trying to get to that the open
eyes and the likes are trying to reach
it's a complex one we do at the core we
know and believe that the set of use
cases where having the highest audio
quality and the highest audio
controlability is going to continue to
to both grow and be the slice that we
want to solve and there's so many other
companies that of course are building
but they usually falter in terms of the
specific quality or building the
solution for a specific use case so
almost the if you think about those two
components is like research will allow
you set of breakthroughs there still the
ones optimized for audio will be where
we can build that Advantage with the
specific data sets that we create and
how we create them and set of
breakthroughs but then the second part
will be increasingly important in the
next five years it will be like how do
you provide that solution that platform
uh element to use the research at scale
and in a good way now what is
interesting like the llm space now is so
much about scale and and getting more
data getting more compute in audio space
we still think it's a little bit earlier
in terms of the breakr that you need to
create to to compress or decompress
audio so that's a good Advantage for us
where we can focus the research
resources and now what will be complex
and that's the part which will be
interesting is today we'll have growing
size of our Audio models where we see
those breakthroughs um and we as you
think about the multimodel experience
will use the LMS that are out there and
fuse them in yeah what would happen if
the open source sto that would be a
potential problem where we don't have
the access to the LMS that are
state-of-the-art in that same way but of
course you have the you like in audio I
think you are still earlier than llms in
terms of diminishing returns in terms of
use cases that are possible so hopefully
by the time potentially companies stop
doing the open source the if they ever
stop it that's unlikely that's a
different sort of conversation exactly
but that would I think for what we can
bring to the table is audio expertise
that that none of those companies ever
focus on and Bling That with LMS will
help and there's so many components in
their research work so we talked about
breakthroughs but even we now have a
team a big team of data labelers that
have voice experience we have voice
coaches that tell them how to understand
audio uh how to annotate the emotions in
the right way so we can then use that
into I think that's the virtual cycle is
around you get the product you get more
users but that in turn gets you more
data which in turns allows you to do it
and I think the more uh specific the
domain is the more you can accumulate
data that that is unique so very cool I
would love to see the sort of the
Innovations on it have all sorts of like
deep thoughts about the uh open weights
model even open sources is like a little
I guess some of them in audio some of
them are actually truly open source but
uh but a lot of them and that's its own
ratle here yeah they are pretty pretty
bad conversations and also the yeah and
the Strategic kind of aspect of it one
of the key distinctions making them not
to Rattle too much here but like key
distinctions making them my beefs with
them is that they're not really open
even the open weights they're more
freeware but because in part you can't
the community can Fork it and continue
it if they behind them chooses not to
not to continue releasing but some of
them indeed in the audio space are
trully open source true the audio ones
are so there are some recent good ones
especially on the architecture that that
we've seen that we created in 2024 there
is like now good examples but and they
are truly open but there's always that
lag that and that lag is an an
interesting one even as we think about
our approaches like what is the lag
which you can still build the advantage
on and we think we can especially
because we are at the Forefront of audio
and like our goal is to to roughly be a
year in front of anything that's
possible out there so to make this to
continue making this TR we need to
release our model in this quarter the
new model which I think is possible
that's the kind of The Guiding Light for
the research work but it'll be
interesting five years is a tricky
question in general yeah it's hard it's
uh in this world it's uh in this at this
space it's hard to imagine it yeah hey
time flies and there's like I've got a
million more sort of subsequent
questions but I want to spend maybe the
last sort of few minutes here talking a
little bit about organiz ation and so
you you already described the sort of
focused research organization on it the
tiny and high impact team and the
product you've published a controversial
decision that you've that you've made
just unusual uh on it in which you've
shoed titles you have no titles in at 11
Labs yeah I guess just open up like can
you tell us a bit more about what it is
that you decided to do there and what
was what drove it so we are now team of
over 100 soon approaching the the magic
number of the 150
but is behind the scenes really it's
more like a team of 20 teams of five or
like 10 teams of five to 10 depending on
the specific period of time and that's
what we try to do it's like extremely
small high degree of ownership High
degree of Independence and they can just
run which helps us move with building on
one side of course the research but very
specific solutions that go deep uh very
specific markets where we try to get
through the goto Market part and and
that responsibility is there that high
degree of both impact and owners is
there now because it's and that's how we
think about effectively nurturing that
flat organization where almost everybody
is in ic like you are expected to to do
a lot of that IC IC work and and where
we are today is down to ic's pushing the
barrier was possible so for IC is being
individual contributor if anybody's off
the acronym here sorry yes that's right
and the thing that we wanted to create
is an environment where people feel that
when they join this organization
especially at this stage where things
are moving so quickly they can have any
size of impact in any amount of short
period of time where they join they can
have that impact and the title shouldn't
be a limiting piece in terms of how much
or how you are what's the perspective on
you from the others in the organization
so that was the first one like impact
shouldn't be defined by the title it
should be defined by individuals no
titles helps that you can get anywhere
in the organization and and and bring
those ideas forward second there's this
concept of the uh and I discussed some
questions in social media that we are
trying to keep the best idea wins where
you have new people they are expected
and also they we know they are great
people that can contribute on on on day
one and and we want to keep that that
that idea that if you join others are
there that you can that you can compete
on those ideas of course if there's like
a really no no decision making we have
team leads for those each five team five
people teams that will make that end
decision and then so they are identified
leads even though they are yeah they
they don't have a t but everybody knows
who's the sort of the lead exactly and
the structure that we have is as you
think about those teams that structure
is heavily evolving still so we wanted
to keep a little bit of the of the
dynamism on that higher level of like
how we are thinking about restructuring
and that is all to say that as we think
about the future those structures will
solidify in some ways and maybe there
will be a good point to introduce those
titles that give that that that that
element of additional recognition and
understanding for new joiners of who is
where and who is doing what but at this
stage impact matters ownership matters
the best idea wins and and and is a
distraction for climbing a ladder that
that we don't want to nurture where now
you are building for the entire company
not building for a specific component
you probably heard about all those ways
U of like how the frequently when the
companies build themselves they they
have a team and the individuals build
for their team rather than for the
company and of course those should be
align but not always are so that that
hopefully helps avoid us but then on the
other side which is the tricky thing of
of your question of like on how that's
on on some of the thinking is that you
do want to keep the some form of
recognition and we are now investing in
different ways of recognizing the
individuals by being much more open in
terms of our releases of the work we do
on like who created that release giving
them credit and giving that element out
there and then there's always this
interesting thing of how the titles can
inflate the or the inflation of titles
in the organization there many problems
that might exist with that titles but I
think like behind the scenes not
everybody gets paid the same and there's
an element of seniority whether within
11 Labs or uh past experience on it that
you would
put different type of sort of
expectations right if you're paying
someone 100 Grand you'd have different
expectations than someone you're paying
200 Grands from them so you know you
want if the person getting the lower
salary there has an amazing idea you
want to allow them to unleash it and
drive it but at the same time you're not
really looking at them the same as an
employer or as a boss I guess how do you
think about because the risk with the
step of change which I I absolutely see
the appeal of it although I am um I have
doubts around its ability to scale and
so maybe it's also right for now and not
right for later um but I think the risk
really is that there's a still seniority
it's just hidden instead of putting it
on people's uh titles I guess how do you
I assume I'm not wrong about the salary
comment and so how do you control for
kind of hidden seniority versus explicit
one yeah and you mentioned also like a
line which I will echo which is like
right for now maybe not right for later
and that's exactly how we approach many
of those decisions is here we think it's
the right moment for current state where
that organization is evolving as a whole
and likely we'll need some other
component or structure in the future
second on your structure piece our
structure is actually very clear and
transparent so we know who the teams are
who is the person responsible How They
Roll Up further up most of those teams
are small so they are those equal levels
but it starts to now create that so we
still have a clear and identified leads
that everybody knows there's no you
don't have the title attribute that is
going to stay and be there forever
because we expect that it's more an
assignment than it is a uh than it is a
title you're not a manager you are
currently managing this team exactly
exactly um so that that structure um is
still very transparent um and the well
the compensation is an interesting one
because given that the nature of our
work which we do have the research
engineering some of the individuals in
those teams or even in the product teams
are acceptional and wants to do those
more of the individual contributing work
of course you you do pay a lot for that
caliber of talent so maybe where I'm
going with this is standard organization
like if you're a manager you are paid
usually more as you think about the
progression than the individual
contributor path and in our case we see
there's like some of the people that are
I's can be paid
more or as much as any of the other
people and want to make sure that this
is something that people know that if
you are a brilliant mind you can have
that in them in any part of course it's
harder because you need to be truly
exceptional but definitely possible I
think look at I think it's very
interesting I've toyed with it as a
thought in the past never as bold a
statement as as what you've you've done
here and I think I do think the sort of
the stage question is is an interesting
one so it's interesting to evolve I have
only I guess the one more immediate sort
of challenge I have for you is just as
you think if you hearken back to the
product versus research type lens on it
or what's the center as you build up a
bigger sales organization a bigger
support organization product
organizations it are you hoping I I
appreciate the sort of humility of maybe
not right for later maybe yes but is
your anticipation that those would also
fit here or do you think hey this works
as long as we as our sort of Center is
this type of activity and that's also an
interesting one and like one thing that
I think is also valuable for us is that
what
it one we did have a number of people
that really wanted us well that hey we
don't think titles are useful there's a
a good internal support for making the
move but then also externally as we
think about hiring Talent we want people
that will join for for that impact that
they can bring to organization which
allows us actually to hire a lot more
people that traditionally are in the
senior level some of the organizations
because they're really joining to right
to execute for the company rather for
they don't need a title of it exactly
which actually helped and like we have
now number of people incredible people
that are reaching with that expectation
that if they are doing well and rightly
they will have high degree of the
ownership in the company you did ask the
right thing which is of course there's a
lot of external roles where the title
itself can be helpful as people interact
with the clients as they get the sale
there are some markets where title is
the way of gaining and and understanding
the respect and here
we we are avoiding this as a so you
don't still have a title because then
everybody would would have a high title
but in a transient exchanges if you
think that the title can help you in a
specific business activity that you do
you are allowed to use it you just we
have like roughly of pre-agreed of what
is the right what is legitimate but but
like good example is Japanese Market
where people really need to know who you
are interacting with where you do use
that in in some of the business contexts
or if you are out bounding to a client
we do potentially allow that we've
actually not seen any of the positive of
if you have a title it like leads to any
better out bounding conversion right
yeah um in presentations too if you are
saying you're leading a region that's as
good enough as I don't know VP or
director head of yeah and I think that
part I wholeheartedly agree with and we
do the same we don't have any sort of VP
or director or such we have head of we
have lead of a team on it here at Tes uh
it was harder to do it 12200 people that
sneak it's interesting hey we're really
coming on time here just one kind of
final question Beyond The Amazing future
that 11 Labs I'm sure has ahead of it
and you'll build a lot what other aspect
of AI excites you the most when you cast
your eyes out I think the I I feel like
this is a common answer you get but it
is extremely exciting of how the LM or
the multimodal space will evolve and
like how can you have even higher degree
of understanding like effectively that
infinite context window or like pretty
large context window and as I think
about education space as a whole and how
Ai and education space can come together
I think this would be incredible if
somebody knew all the knowledge I gained
over the last since I was born can be my
personal tutor through that through
those years be my like matatics voice
when I'm solving mathematical problem
and then help me on this sales deal that
that they haven't known about the
process which will be an interesting
innovation in terms of can the llm space
or multimodal space carry that that very
large context across my life and provide
that personalized experience so I think
what what companies like on Tropic X
openi are doing on the on that side or
Google is this is incredible for the
world and for what's possible yeah oh
exciting to see that as well Ms is
amazing I really wish you all the best
on it and I really love the insights
that you shared over here so huge thanks
for coming on to the show thank you guys
thanks for having me it was a pleasure
speaking together and thanks everybody
for tuning in and I hope you join us for
the next
one you're listening to the AI native
Dev brought to you by Tesla
[Music]